Ellen Fenton Diaries of Travels to Boulogne-sur-Mer
Yale Center for British Art, Rare Books and Manuscripts
- Diaries
  - Diary, 1856 August 20-September 2; Fenton, Ellen, b. circa 1813; 1 volume (100 pages), 20 pages of watercolor drawings; 4 receipts; 3 playbills; 1 letter; 1 musical score; c. 32.5 x 20.5 cm. (Box Vol. 4)
    With "Dick" and his friend Amor, Fenton embarks on an excursion to the Chateau d'Hardelot near Condette "because Charles Edward the Pretender was once secreted near there" (92). She is perturbed to find her donkey has an open wound and scolds the men who rented it to her for their cruelty. Hiring another donkey, they reach St. Etienne church, which, along with the panoramic views, make good sketching subjects. When it begins to rain, Fenton and the boys seek shelter at an auberge, thinking they might have to sleep there. Fenton derives great amusement from her jokes that Amor would have to sleep upstairs with the peasant household "numbered twelve" (93). The rain abates, and they continue on to the "garennes" ( sand hills), where the donkeys can go no farther. Fenton admires the "stretching-out hills, undulating gracefully, of sand, with the rushes, for verdure, and on one side the sea" (94). Fenton includes herself in a painted scene, along with her peasant guide and a child who took her parasol: "For a moment, I felt frightened, standing here alone in the wet, and under the darkening sky, when the thought arose these people might be a lawless set" (95). Taking a growing interest in Clara's beauty, Fenton tends to embellish her entries about Clara in this fair copy. At the pier, she writes that three Englishmen are overheard exclaiming "Ah! Here's the prettiest girl in Boulogne" and following her, joke "Let's see if she twigs!" (99-100). One man "most perservering" has a room in the attic at the Hotel, overlooking Clara's room so she has too keep her curtains drawn at all times. Fenton claims she overhears two maids in the hotel yard talking of Dall and Dada at the breakfast window, saying "Oui – elle est belle… mais ce n'est pas d'elle qu'on parle. Clest une plus grande" (Yes, she is beautiful… but it's not her that is spoken of. It's an older one). (103) A bit of a voyeur herself, Fenton is intent on spying on a gentleman through the window of a "luxurious room" (116). She only ever sees the back of his head, reading "continually until daybreak" and sketches him this way (see drawing, this volume). At the Tintilleries Ball on September 3rd, Fenton watches on as Clara and "Mr. Hamilton" dance the schottische, polka, quadrille, and varsovienne. She praises Clara's dignified manner, noting she is "without a shadow of affectation of pretension. She wore her hat and veil down, and looked beautiful, through it."(142). When Clara tears her dress while dancing, Fenton is delighted to see Mr. Hamilton offer little "housewife pins, to arrange the torn flounces." (143) She revels in what she perceives as "jealous looks" of all the English gentlemen watching Mr. Hamilton save the day.
    A number of English visitors enliven the Fentons's stay in Boulogne. Mr. Sharpe spends an evening at Boulogne, and Fenton is happy to see him dancing with Clara at the Tintilleries ball. She is equally happy to report that Mr. and Mrs. Tarleton (nicknamed 'Roly Poly' by Fred) will arrive at Boulogne, and Mrs. Tarleton's letter is pasted into this volume. Fenton resolves to stay an additional week in Boulogne to prolong their time with the Tarletons, at young Fred's urges. Amor is also a delight to Fenton. When Dick goes to see a lecture by Mr. Lewis about "mesmerism and biology," Amor refuses to accompany him, because the last time he and others were "paraded, as susceptibles on Mr. Lewis' platform, and did all manner of nonsense" (120). "Mr. Lewis told him he was Prince Albert, and his troops waited to be surveyed, and Amor walked forward, as if with a telescope and strutted about, and after a long pause, muttered A fine body of men!'" (127). Fenton is amused that Amor is frequently in petty fights with boys his own age around town. One particular boy is hated by Amor for being Clara's admirer and follower, and Fenton's footnote reveals that he was "Douglas Willans, the "Julian of my Boulogne 1857 journal" (See Volume 6) (139). He and Dick spend their time roaming around, looking for crabs, which get loose and "make the cook scream" (141).
    Setting out solo towards the Notre Dame basilica, Fenton expresses her annoyance at being chaperoned by two strangers: "I own I felt rather staggered to be thus in their charge, and had much rather have gone alone" (125). At the side of the old church, Fenton describes the remnants of war with English – ruins of broken pillars, square cells, and cannon balls from English ships. She makes another trip with Dick to visit the cathedral, and they climb the rickety scaffolding towards the dome. Both frightened by the height, they are only able to take in the view of the sea from the arched windows before turning back, trembling.
    On outdoor excursions, Fenton has a heightened awareness of the limitations of art in capturing fleeting nature, as evidenced in her comments about sketching excursions. When she seats herself near the Napoleon monument to execute a "large sketch," she muses: "then I had one of those few but most happy episodes in my life, when I forget all but the joyful present…. Wonderful it was to watch the play of shadows, from the clouds, on the wide waters. Ever changing, and each change seeming more lovely than the other. What hues of violet and green there were, and the gold lights from the sun! and yet my picture is tame and cold, and grieves me, as a painting. I closed my eyes to say 'all is now gone – a dream" (134).
    Fenton is intent on going home to England via an alternate route – first stopping at Rouen to see a play, and then by steamship from Le Havre – but her husband writes, "begging me to give up this journey" (145). Abandoning the idea, the family board the usual steamer back to London, and Fenton is thrilled by the chance to spend two hours on deck, "in shawl, and blankets… I laid upon a Bench near the steersman. It was such perfect luxury to see thus, the starlit heavens and lie in sweet repose. I rejoiced in all – the rushing air – the very bounding of the steamer – the sound of the paddle wheels" (151). In a watercolor drawing, she depicts the unusual scene. She finishes her journal by enumerating the paintings that she has framed "lightly, in that new way, with paper" for her home as a remembrance of the trip (not included in these journals). She also ends with an apology of sorts, to her reader: "and now I must beg indulgence, if my journal has failed to amuse. What subject could be more commonplace – what journey so poor a bit of travelling, as a mere excursion to Boulogne! (154)"
    Watercolors; Sketchbooks; Travel sketches -- France; Boulogne-sur-Mer (France) -- Views; Boulogne-sur-Mer (France) -- Description and travel; Diaries; Fenton, Ellen, b. circa 1813 -- Diaries; Basilica of Notre Dame (Boulogne-sur-mer, France)
  - Diary, 1856 August 2-26; Fenton, Ellen, b. circa 1813; 1 volume (84 pages); c. 32 x 20 cm. (Box Vol. 5)
    Holograph diary describing Ellen Fenton's family vacation at Boulogne-sur-mer, 1857. This first volume would be later worked up into Fenton's fair copies of her 1856 diaries (Volumes 3 and 4). The existence of this draft version suggests that Fenton created preliminary drafts for all of her journals, though this is the only one present. The handwriting, as well as prose style, is less legible in this draft volume than in subsequent volumes. She also sometimes uses different names for her children – particularly for her youngest child, "Titchey" or "Titchet" who is referred to in the fair copies as "Hal".
    Some of the details are later embellished, and Fenton uses the names of family and friends in the draft volume whereas she uses pseudonyms or crosses out names in later drafts. Small adjustments aside, much of the information is repeated verbatim in the fair copy volumes.
    Boulogne-sur-Mer (France) -- Description and travel; Diaries; Fenton, Ellen, b. circa 1813 -- Diaries
  - Diary, 1857 August 22-September 14; Fenton, Ellen, b. circa 1813; 1 volume (112 pages); 17 pages of watercolor and pen & ink drawings; 2 receipts; 1 funeral notice; 1 playbill; c. 32.5 x 20.5 cm. (Box Vol. 6)
    Holograph diary describing Ellen Fenton's family vacation at Boulogne-sur-Mer, 1857. Includes seventeen pages of watercolor drawings and pen & ink sketches of local people, scenery and landscapes to accompany journal descriptions. This volume contains one drawing by Fenton's daughter 'Deeny' of a "Boulogne Procession," and the unfinished and varying quality of this volume's sketches suggests that some of the other Fenton children may have made contributions. A funeral notice for "Mme Boisselot" is included, as well as a playbill for the theatrical performances Manche à Manche, Marivaudage, and Le Bénéficaire.
    On Saturday the 22nd of August, Ellen Fenton reports that she and her family made arrangements to depart once more for Boulogne. Fenton laments the absence of Viv and Dick, the latter studying at a "Mr Scheibs School" in Frankfurt. As in 1854, Fenton quarrels with the steamship porters over the placement of her hamper of provisions, insisting it remain with the family in their cabin.
    With Dick away, Fenton's motherly affections are very much directed towards her youngest, Hal (Henry), who supplies her with endless amusement with his observations and his ability to attract attention from strangers. Fenton is also increasingly preoccupied with Clara, and attends numerous balls and entertainments with her daughter, whom she guards very closely. She takes frequent jabs at Clara's potential suitors, giving them all nicknames such as "Fergus" and "Firebrand." Though Clara seems indifferent, Fenton seems to take a particular liking to one young "elegant" man, whom she fondly calls "Julian." Fenton calls Julian's chaperones and companions (possibly elder brothers) "the Romans" for their Roman noses, and her footnote indicates these young men are "the Mr. Douglas-Willans of Twyford Abbey" (which had just a few months prior been leased through an Act of Parliament by the widow Isabella Maria Douglas Willan upon--see the London Gazette, July 3, 1857, page 2353) (77). As Fenton increasingly takes interest in Julian, 'Appa,' who joins the family at Boulogne, "pretends to be quite angry because we talk of [him]" (80). While her husband rebuffs the young men who talk to Clara, Fenton acts as Clara's proxy by engaging with young men on her behalf.
    This year, the Fentons take up temporary lodging on the Rue Percée, across from the Communale College gates, which gives them ample opportunity to observe the Catholic worshippers, priests, and nuns enter and exit the grounds opposite. Fenton makes no attempts to disguise her anti-Catholic fear and prejudice: "I have so imbued my children with the idea the Catholics watch the Protestants, that Dada came from a window at breakfast time, sideline, with a look of terror, and whispered, 'The Priest peept again!!'"
    The position of their lodgings also gives the Fentons full view of the processions of pilgrims passing through Boulogne, some with offerings for the Cathedral and the "Fete" that unfolds over the course of several days (the Fete Napoleon and the Virgin's birthday occur during their stay). Fenton reports that the landlord's servant, Mary, is fearful that the Catholics mean to convert her daughter, who attends a school run by the local nuns. Fenton uses Mary as a means of explicating the merits of Protestantism in contrast to Catholic practices, plying the servant with arguments "that it had internal evidence that became more and more convincing... Christ was the 'only Mediator' but as God only is omnipresent… how could these Saints hear our prayers, from people at all quarters of the world, at the same period?" (33). Though Fenton remonstrates Catholic ritual, she takes pleasure in describing the customs and dress of the procession participants, down to the smallest detail. The image of a friar in bare feet, shaven head, bearing a "painful sight of willing misery and want," causes Fenton to reflect on the supposed paradox that "he and the richly dressed luxurious Cardinal were representing the same religion" (32). Emotionally conflicted about her own participation in the throng, Fenton nevertheless persists in watching the spectacle. When the Archbishop of Dublin comes to bless members of the crowd, Clara refuses to kneel: "His grand face looked at her, with such a tremendously commanding air, many would have quailed. I almost shook for her. I think we erred in taking such prominent places. The Protestants should, in better taste, be at the windows" (44).
    This volume is punctuated by frequent social calls with Fenton's sister, Elizabeth "Lizzie" Russel and family. The Fentons and the Russel girls--Minnie, Ada, and Janie--attend Balls together. General Russel, Lizzie's husband, particularly gets along with "Appa" (John Fenton), as they are united by their dislike of Boulogne: "Both my tiresome 'Appa' and the General rail against Boulogne, and wonder what we find to like here! I tell them I am thankful for every hour" (99).
    Some of the volume's most amusing incidents involve Fenton's descriptions of French visitors and locals. Fenton describes two funny young Parisians riding the omnibus, one of whom she calls "fat Albert" and two "rotten handsome moustached beaux" (55). She draws an amusing portrait of the latter pair: "one perched on the shoulders of the other, who was smoking, while he, aloft, was eating tarts!" (55). Another incident described at length is the loss of Clara's hairpin. Fenton hires a town crier to announce the lost pin, and within an hour it is brought back, "smashed to pieces" by a group of "fishpeople" (78). When they demand 3 francs for the pin, Fenton cannot tolerate such a request: "Vous pensez me tromper, vous! Vous me pensez une pauvre anglaise, qui ne connait rien? N'essayez pas ca, car je vous dit, que je suis Boulounaise!! Si vous ne voulez pas ces dix sous, prenez l'epingle, et jettez le dans la mer, et notre affaire est finie. Allez!" ["You think to wrong me! You think me a poor Englishwoman who knows nothing? You [would] not try that were I Boulonaise!! If you do not want the ten sous, take the pin and throw it into the sea, and our business is finished. Go!"]. The expressions of astonishment on their faces after this outburst prompts Fenton to recall this as "one of the best scenes I have had here" (78).
    Diaries; Watercolors; Travel sketches -- France; Boulogne-sur-Mer (France) -- Views; Boulogne-sur-Mer (France) -- Description and travel; Fenton, Ellen, b. circa 1813 -- Diaries; Fenton, Henry John Horstman, 1854-1929
  - Diary, 1857 September 14-September 29; Fenton, Ellen, b. circa 1813; 1 volume (118 pages), 28 pages of watercolor drawings; 1 list; c. 32.5 x 20.5 cm. (Box Vol. 7)
    Continuation of Ellen Fenton's holograph journal, describing a family vacation at Boulogne-sur-Mer, 1857. Includes twenty-eight pages of watercolor drawings featuring local people, scenery and landscapes to accompany journal descriptions. This volume also contains a hand-written list of "Objects [sic] Cassée" [broken objects], most likely charged to Fenton by her landlord at the conclusion of the family's stay.
    Although she extols the simplicity and 'picturesque' nature of the Boulogne fish quarter, Fenton nevertheless reveals her prejudice against its inhabitants' hygiene. She describes one fisherwoman who stood watching her and the children, with hair "which I am sure had not been combed for years. It was red, and tossed up all round her – indeed thrown matted and tangled anywhere" (109; she includes a drawing of the woman on a subsequent page). When Hal goes missing for a few hours, she finds him sitting on the knee of her French landlord, M. Andrieux. She "rebels against the idea of his dirty red bristles of moustaches on Hal's face," hastily whisking him away to procure a comb from the hairdresser next-door (111). During an excursion, Fenton seeks permission to sketch the Chateau of the Comte de Bethune at an attached house on the grounds, and is "amazed… to see the exceeding poverty of the house. Good rooms but oh the dirt, dust and spiders!" (122).
    Fenton hires a "cariole"--an older type of carriage--for a picnic, which they dub the "funny carriage" (see 191). Though Fenton prefers that Clara not be seen in "such a strange carriage," it is a topic of great amusement, and the youngest children "had not a thought about the disgrace or honor" of it (115). They stop at a farm, where she takes a moment to sketch the Chateau of the Comte de Bethune, adjacent. Fenton helps the farmhouse landlady make bread, and the two speak about the recent events of the Indian mutiny (123). The coachman teaches Fenton's servant how to play skittles. Fenton runs into the woods and finds the "most wild, quiet bowery spot I ever remember" (124). The ride back in the fog reminds Fenton of a childhood carriage ride on her nurse's knee, traveling all over France, when the carriage wheel came off as they approached Versailles.
    Missy Macleod, a friend of Dall's, arrives from England to stay with the Fenton's during their holiday and the two girls are inseparable. They like to imitate the landlord, whom they nickname "Grubbins" (see 167), and a beggar named Pierre Olivier with an affected tremble, whom they call "trembler" (see portrait, page 165). Meanwhile, Fenton takes Clara and the eldest Russel girls to several balls, where they attract the attention and jealousies of French and English alike. Fenton takes several opportunities to converse with Julian (see portrait, page 134), while guarding him against his chaperones, the "Romans." Fenton is thrilled when Julian offers to walk Clara home: "he is so gentlemanly and graceful" (138). Fenton includes a particularly finished watercolor of Julian doffing his hat to Clara (189).
    Despite the rigid formal interactions at the ball, Fenton's journal provides glimpses into her more spontaneous activities at Boulogne. There are several instances of Fenton's good humour and her ability to spontaneously adapt to circumstances. On a picnic excursion, they hire the same "funny carriage" and a large horse, however the old horse struggles going up a hill and Fenton breaks a parasol in town by pushing the carriage from behind. The horse falls on some stones and breaks its ankle, and the family is stranded under a tree while the coachman brings replacement horses (143). Not deterred from travel, Fenton and Clara hire donkeys on another day to take them to the "Colonne" overlooking the Vallée du Nacre, topped with a "colossal figure in bronze on top" (150). Always adventuresome, Fenton inquires whether it would be possible to sleep a night in one of the sea forts. For fun, she tries to convince the confectioner Mademoiselle Desir to sleep in the fort with her, conjuring "the animals, the wind, the noise," and sketches the confectioner's reactions to entertaining such an idea (153). Resolved to go alone, she enquires at the police station, where they say it has been closed for the winter. She and her daughters, with the nurses, walk out to sea one evening, and swim in the phosphorescent sea: "We soon undressed, and put on our night gowns, and ran in…. Wherever the water rippled only, or was touched, it sparkled with stars" (186). Fenton sketches the scene on page 155.
    Diaries; Boulogne-sur-Mer (France) -- Description and travel; Boulogne-sur-Mer (France) -- Views; Travel sketches -- France; Watercolors; Fenton, Ellen, b. circa 1813 -- Diaries
  - Diary, 1860 July 17-August 11; Fenton, Ellen, b. circa 1813; 1 volume (134 pages); 11 pages of watercolor drawings; 3 letters; 1 playbill; 1 programme; 2 clippings; c. 32.5 x 20.5 cm. (Box Vol. 8)
    Holograph journal describing Ellen Fenton's family vacation at Boulogne-sur-Mer, 1860. Includes eleven pages of watercolor drawings of local people, scenery and landscapes to accompany journal descriptions. On page eleven, Fenton also includes a sketch of the Colonnade ballroom floor plan. This volume contains letters from Fanny Crawford and Officer Crawford (of the 15th Bombay Regiment), clippings of "The Pope's Irish recruits" from 27 July 1860 and "To Englishmen Settling in Boulogne" and a playbill for Le Songe.
    Fenton does not hesitate to announce the presence of Geraldine Ibotson at Boulogne. The majority of Fenton's journal entries are devoted to her young female friend, who accompanies the family on their annual holiday. Fenton appears to have endless admiration for Geraldine's beauty and grace: "how noble she looked! Never could the stately Duchess of Sutherland, in her grandest youth, have looked such a Duchess!" (4). Geraldine usurps Clara's usual position as the object of admiration, and Fenton amuses herself with conjectures about the many beaux who take interest in the new arrival. Fenton delights in describing the dandyish Monsieur Horeau, whom they nickname "Henrietta," and his pursuit of Geraldine. A bouquet and a book about love letters in French arrives at the Fenton's residence "and a marked passage about a declaration of love! We all suspected Henrietta" (70). Geraldine cannot seem to do any wrong in the eyes of her loyal chaperone, and she believes that none but the most sophisticated of men would comprehend "the rich contradictions of her character, so great and yet so childish, religious yet gay, earnest and yet so willing for nonsense. None but a poet, and one of versatile talent and very close observation, would understand her" (70). When she pays a visit to Mrs Russell, a wealthy Australian who resides at the Chateau Neuf, Fenton is taken aback by the governess's attacks on Geraldine's character. The governess claims she saw Geraldine "on Saturday, flirting with a gentleman, and she had felt ashamed of her countrywoman for her conduct, which was such that everyone was staring, and more, laughing, at her, that she was a disgrace" (86). Fenton counters by describing Mrs. Ibotson's model education of her daughters, and slips in "that one of her girls was 'the present Belle of Boulogne'" (87).
    Although she rushes to Geraldine's defense, Fenton has no trouble describing the faults of others. She is irked by the governess's claims that Mademoiselle Dion was "unsurpassed" in beauty. This mademoiselle is believed to be the Marchioness Déhon, whom Fenton sketches (between pages 24 and 25). Fenton takes pleasure in describing the noblewoman's haughty and poor conduct, conceding that Dion is "pretty – a porcelain sort of look, reminding one of those old fashioned figures on Dresden China" (38). She is disgusted by the young woman's demands to be attended first at restaurants. When standing at a newspaper table at a ball, Fenton overhears some English gossip about Dion's faults in earshot of the marchioness. Fenton then delights in describing the young woman flee in a rage, banging doors behind her. "Dick ran to the door, and banged it again – which she seemed to return, by an explosion of another door… thus, when she [Dion] sat at our table, Geraldine aloud asked me, if I had heard the strange banging of doors, at the other end of the room… I said, I supposed it could only be servants" (43).